VAHIDULLAH TAC

Data-Driven Modeling of Soft Materials

Mechanics & Mechanobiology Lab, Purdue University

765 532 2780 tacvahid@gmail.com www.tajtac.com github.com/tajtac linkedin.com/in/tajtac

Summary: Senior PhD student working on data-driven modeling of soft materials. I specialize in combining physics and machine learning, imposing hard constraints on machine learning methods, uncertainty quantification with Bayesian Neural Networks and developing strategies for training neural networks with reduced data.

EDUCATION _

PhD Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA

2021 - now Mechanical Engineering

Dissertation title: Data-driven modeling of biological materials

MSc Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

2016 - 2019 Aerospace Engineering

Thesis title: Micromechanical modeling of carbon nanotube – polymer composites

BSc Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

2012 - 2016 Aerospace Engineering

EXPERIENCE _____

Purdue Research Assistant

2021 - now

- **University** Developed a model of hyperelastic material behavior based on feed-forward neural networks in Python/TensorFlow.
 - Used special properties of Neural ODEs to develop a model of hyperelasticity where physics-based constraints are satisfied a priori using Python/JAX. This approach circumvents the use of a complicated loss function thus avoiding a large number of unnecessary floating-point operations.
 - Developed the first physics-informed data-driven model of finite viscoelasticity in the world. The project uses Neural ODEs to model viscoelasticity in such a way that the relevant physical laws are satisfied automatically.
 - Currently working on a hierarchical Bayesian model of hyperelasticity using Bayesian Neural Networks (BNNs) in Python/Numpyro. The model can characterize the uncertainty in training data and transfer knowledge from the population to an individual.

Turkish Structural Design Engineer

Aerospace 2018 - 2021

 Designed various spacecraft parts such as structural panels, inserts and brackets. Spearheaded the development of the first structural panel with embedded active cooling in TAI.

Technologies Research Institute

2017 - 2018

TUBITAK Space Research Engineer

• Developed two engineering software packages for 1) conceptual aircraft design and 2) prediction of failure modes of composite materials using Visual Basic and MATLAB. The packages received praise for being user friendly and responsive.

PUBLICATIONS

- [6] V. Tac, M. K. Rausch, F. S. Costabal and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven anisotropic finite viscoelasticity using neural ordinary differential equations," in review at Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2023.
- [5] V. Tac, K. Linka, F. S. Costabal, E. Kuhl and A. B. Tepole, "Benchmarks for physics-informed data-driven hyperelasticity," in review at Computational Mechanics, 2023.
- [4] V. Tac, F. S. Costabal, and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven tissue mechanics with polyconvex neural ordinary differential equations," Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2022.
- [3] V. Tac, V. D. Sree, M. K. Rausch, and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven modeling of the mechanical behavior of anisotropic soft biological tissue," Engineering with Computers, 2022.
- [2] Y. Leng, V. Tac, S. Calve, and A. B. Tepole, "Predicting the mechanical properties of biopolymer gels using neural networks trained on discrete fiber network data," Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2021.
- [1] V. Tac and E. Gürses, "Micromechanical modelling of carbon nanotube reinforced composite materials with a functionally graded interphase," Journal of Composite Materials, 2019.

AWARDS &

HONORS

- Robert J. Melosh Medal for best student paper in computational solid mechanics, Duke University, 2022
- Ward A. Lambert Graduate Fellowship, Purdue University, 2022
- Ben M. Hillberry Graduate Scholarship, Purdue University, 2022
- 3rd Place, Individual Aircraft Design Competition 2015-16, American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA).
- 1st Place, METU Engineering Day 2016 Poster Competition

SKILLS ____

- Python (Proficient in JAX and familiar with TensorFlow and PyTorch)
- Machine learning (Extensive experience with Neural ODEs)
- FORTRAN
- Finite Element Method
- Familiarity with a variety of tools and languages such as Julia, Visual Basic, MATLAB, C, HTML, Javascript, PHP, IATEX and others.